Mazel tov today's דף daf is י"ט Yud Tet and we kick
off at the bottom of י"ח עמוד ב' Yud Chet Amud Bet
and we are talking about the different פושקא, pushka, that's not the
right word but
anyway שופרות, shofarot, the different money boxes that they had in the
בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash for different types of donations and when people
would donate different things and they would give the money for it.
It talked about logs of wood and incense and gold. And now
there were six, so we went through the first seven which were
very specific. And now there were six which were all נדבה, nedava,
which is also we know termed elsewhere קיץ המזבח, Keitz HaMizbeiach, which
is עולות olot that would go for to be brought on the
מזבח mizbeiach when it was not there was no other activity to
keep things busy and active. And also one you could give straight
to this fund, but also money that was left over from a
חטאת chatat or an אשם asham would also go into this fund
and the משנה mishnah even had the פסוק pasuk and even said
that the כהנים kohanim or who was it, one of the כהן,
kohen, יהוידע הכהן Yehoyada HaKohen was it, interpreted this פסוק. pasuk. Okay,
יהוידע כהן גדול. Yehoyada Kohen Gadol. So let's take a look at
the גמרא. gemara. ששה נדבה. Shisha nedava. It is about eight lines
from the bottom, there is a ב bet in parentheses. רב Rav
or חזקיה Chizkiya אמר amar כנגד ששה בתי אבות, kineged shisha batei
avot, corresponding to the six בתי אבות batei avot which was the
each משמר. mishmar. The כהנים kohanim were divided into twenty-four משמרות, mishmarot,
so each משמר mishmar functioned about twice a year and then each
משמר mishmar was subdivided into family houses and each family house operates
one day a week, six family houses, one of the one day
of that משמר mishmar's week and everybody together on שבת. Shabbat. So
corresponding to those ששה בתי אבות. shisha batei avot. Now you could
just say sometimes, again, this is always the issue with the word
כנגד. kineged. Does כנגד kineged mean corresponding to like you know a
symbolic number? So here is a nice number corresponding. Or do we
actually mean that it is you know it links to, like when
we had you bowed down כנגד kineged the thirteen openings, the thirteen
gates, that meant literally physically opposite. So here too, as we are
going to see, כנגד kineged does not just mean it was a
nice number but really the question is what? Was there six times
as much money given for the נדבה nedava as for everything else?
Why did you need six times as many שופר, shofar, you know
this had six, everything else had one. So the answer is that
כנגד kineged here seems to be it was exactly corresponding to like
one שופר shofar was Sunday and one שופר shofar was Monday and
one was Tuesday like you know written on it or assumed. So
if you put your money in the Sunday שופר shofar that was
used for Sunday קרבנות korbanot and if it was in the Monday
שופר shofar used for Monday קרבנות. korbanot. Now why would you need
to do that? Why couldn't you just have a generic one and
you would draw on it as needed? So let's take a look
at what the גמרא gemara says.
Just a simple logical question, where were all these שופרות? shofarot?
That is a very good question. Like if you wanted to be
there for people to give the money, you would want it like
you know accessible. Was it in the עזרה? azarah? Was it in
the עזרת נשים? ezrat nashim? You would also, even though it is
shaped as a שופר shofar as we said so you can't stick
your hand in, you presumably want it under some form of supervision
as well. So that is an excellent question. I don't know the
answer to that. Okay. So בר פדייה Bar Pedaiah אמר, amar, so
the first answer is ששה בתי אבות shisha batei avot and as
we will see it's for the reason I said so that each
family knows which one is its שופר, shofar, each you know each
בית אב. beit av. We will see why. But first we have
another answer which clearly just means well let's take a look. בר
פדייה Bar Pedaiah אמר amar כנגד ששה בהמות, kineged shisha behemot, six
types of animals: פר ועגל, par ve-egel,
a cow and a calf; שעיר, sa'ir, a goat; איל וגדי; ayil
ve-gedi; שעיר איל, sa'ir ayil, a young you know a goat, an
איל, ayil, a ram; גדי, gedi, a young goat; and טלה
taleh and a sheep. So it is interesting they in a way
broke up the different types of species. It could have said שעיר
וגדי ואיל וטלה. sa'ir ve-gedi ve-ayil ve-taleh. Anyway, six. Now again what
does that mean? Is that just six is a nice number? Does
it mean if you put it in the שור shor then we
took the money from the שור שופר shor shofar to buy שור
עולות shor olot and if you put it in the איל ayil
we brought איל שופרות? ayil shofarot? So it could here mean as
well that it's not that it's just a nice symbolic number but
actually they would be designated for these different purposes.
Did it say it on there?
It presumably or somehow it was assumed or said. Now let's take
a look,
one minute.
Now שמואל Shmuel אמר, amar, and שמואל Shmuel says כנגד ששה קרבנות,
kineged shisha korbanot, six types of קרבנות. korbanot. What are the six
types of קרבנות? korbanot? So you see there's some question here. קיני
זבים וקיני זבות וקיני יולדות, kinei zavim ve-kinei zavot ve-kinei yoldot, that's
difficult to count those because some of those are obligatory. חטאות אשמות
ומנחות ועשירית האיפה, chatatot, ashamot u-menachot ve-asirit ha-eifah, but that really only
gets you four. So as you can imagine there is some question
here about about the גרסא. girsa. Look a חטאת chatat and an
אשם asham is also only obligatory. So presumably but some of the
money as you remember for the נדבה nedava was proceeds of the
חטאת chatat and the אשם, asham, right? So חטאות chatatot and אשמות
ashamot could be money that was proceeds from that. מנחות ועשירית האיפה,
menachot ve-asirit ha-eifah, again it's not exactly clear what this is. Again
the commentator says this was proceeds from left-over money for מנחה mincha
and left-over money for the עשירית האיפה asirit ha-eifah and also this
the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol would bring a קרבן korban every day,
half in the morning half in the afternoon. What? No. But just
like the חטאת chatat and the אשם, asham, any left-over money would
go towards that. Okay. That is six potential different origins for the
money. Now, that you certainly don't understand. Why did we have to
designate out the different question of their origins, at least the question
of what to use the money for. You don't know why it
matters so much, but if you want to say I want to
use it for a cow, I want to use it for a
sheep, or at least know which day you draw the money from,
that makes sense. Why you should have six different ones based on
where they originated is a lot less clear. Okay. Now we have
an explanation at least for the why you would need different days
and why you can't just draw on it communally as needed. So
let's take a look. אמר רבי יוחנן, Amar Rabbi Yochanan, על ידי
שהנדבה מרובה, al yedei she-hanedava meruba, ריבו לו שופרות הרבה. ribbu lo
shofrot harbe. Because there was a lot, they had a lot of
שופרות, shofrot, which seems to be a more mundane answer, which is
just look, there was actually was a lot of money that went
to it. Maybe a lot of extra money for חטאת ואשם, chatat
ve-asham, a lot of people wanted to give to this spot, so
they just had it, it was nothing special. חטאת ואשם chatat ve-asham
was not נדבה.
nedava.
What? No, no, but extra money that was sanctified for חטאת ואשם
chatat ve-asham would go to it and that was in the משנה.
mishna.
Even more than all the שקלים shekalim they would get. What?
Yeah, I know well they would no but they would regularly empty
the שופר shofar and put it into the put it into the
what do you call it? To the לשכה. lishka. Now again, what
is what is not being spelled out here, I'm I'm sorry I
think I let me just check I think in the קרבן העדה
Korban HaEdah I think I just yeah, I'm sorry it was in
the קרבן העדה. Korban HaEdah. What's not being spelled out here is
why you would need a different one for each day, right? Why
you couldn't just draw on communal funds? So if you take a
look at the קרבן העדה Korban HaEdah here, like about five lines
before the lines get wide on the right hand margin he says
the following: כנגד ששת בתי אבות, keneged sheshet batei avot, הכהנים שתיקנו
להם חכמים שיהיו כל משמר חולק לששה בתי אבות, hakohanim shetiknu lahem
chachamim sheyihyu kol mishmar cholek leshisha batei avot, כנגד ששת ימי השבוע,
keneged sheshet yemei hashavua, אחד ביומו, echad beyomo, etcetera. So he said
like this, he said כולם שווים, kulam shavim, שלא יהיה ביניהם, shelo
yehei beineichem, שהעורות של בהמות הניטולות מן השופרות היו לכהנים שמקריבים אותם,
sheha'orot shel behemot hanitolot min hashofrot hayu lakohanim shemakrivim otam, וכל זמן
שאין המזבח בטל היו לוקחים מן השופרות. ve-chol zman she-ein hamizbe'ach batel
hayu lokchim min hashofrot. ואם היה להם אלא שופר אחד, ve-im haya
lahem ela shofar echad, אתו למינצויי, atu le-mintzuyei, שבשלושה ימים של בית
אב הראשון או השני יביאו נדבות הרבה, shebi-shlosha yamim shel beit av
harishon o hasheni yavi'u nedavot harbe, ולא יטול בית אב מן השופר
כלום. ve-lo yitol beit av min hashofar klum. Meaning
basically what happens is like this: if you had a communal fund
of this, then I would basically, you know, my day was Sunday
and your day was Monday, and your day was a non-busy day
and you had and you used a lot of that money to
bring these extra קרבנות, korbanot, and my day was a busy day
and I didn't use any of the money, I would say hey
it's not fair! You got to draw on those funds and your
family got to benefit, because every family that worked that day would
get whatever the benefit is from the קרבנות. korbanot. Would it be
the meat, would it be the skin, whatever קרבן korban were brought
that they would benefit from would be for that day, it would
not be divided amongst the whole week, it would be for the
family that worked that day. So what the קרבן העדה Korban HaEdah
explains this is that you would want it that we wouldn't want
to fight like oh, you got to use more of those funds
on your day than I did on my day. And hey, my
day was just as busy on your day but we didn't draw
on as much of those funds and it's not fair you got
to bring it and you got etc etc. So he says in
order so that there shouldn't be fights, each family had its own
day's box and you would just draw from your day and you
couldn't complain about how the funds were distributed over the course of
the week. I gotta say I don't fully understand it because if
you're not drawing on it, it's because it's your day is busy.
And if your day is busy, when you bring an עולה, olah,
all you get is the skin. So actually what you get from
those proceeds, you actually benefit from is relatively minimal. The other things
it could be busy with is a שלמים, shlamim, is a חטאת,
chatat, right? So there you get a lot more than just the
leather. But whatever it is, he says we don't want there to
be fights about how that was distributed over the week. So we
give each one, each family a different day and let them figure
out for their day how they're going to use those funds.
So then what happens though?
Like let's say it was a busy day and it happens to
be that nobody gave into the Sunday box, and right, and I
yeah and I don't know, I also don't know if they tried
to empty it out at the end of the week. Right, let's
say you had a big filled thing on Sunday, you didn't need
to use it so much, and then the next משמר mishmar came
in. Would they be able to draw on last week's Sunday's box?
I I have no idea.
Okay, you have two shifting traditions and images of the כהונה. kehuna.
On the one hand, they're זריזים, zerizim, they're מדקדקים, medakdekim, you rely
on them for time. Right. On the other hand, they're running up
the כבש kevesh and breaking each other's arms, well
that's I think consistent, and throwing אתרוגים. etrogim.
I
think they're very passionate about everything that's related to this, whether it's,
so I think I actually think it's related. They're not צדיקים, tzaddikim,
okay? They're קנאים, kanaim, they're passionate, they're whatever, okay. So they're מדקדק
medakdek in everything they've got to do, but they're also very, you
know, aggressive in those. I don't, משוגע, meshuga, yeah, I don't I
don't think it's that anyway. But what you have is different explanations,
some is the last one is the most prosaic. You just had
the most money for this, why I don't know, but you had
the most money for it and other explanations really make it to
be
Somehow either distinguishing their origins or distinguishing the uses that they would
go to from different different types of animals or different days of
the week. All right, so now let's continue. כתיב *Ketiv*, the פסוק
pasuk *Pasuk* says, three lines from the bottom. וככלותם הביאו לפני המלך
ויהוידע *Ukhkhallotam heviu lifne hammelekh viyhoyada*, these are the פסוקים *Pesukim*
about the whole, you know, bringing the the the money that was
given for the בדק הבית *Bedek haBayit* etc. רב שמואל Shmuel. בר
נחמני בשם רב יונתן *Rav Shemuel bar Nahmani beshem Rav Yonatan* says
שתי נדבות nedavos עשה *Shte nedavot asa*, they did two types of
donations because in מלכים *Melakhim* it says here if you read the
קרבן korban העדה *Korban HaEdah* quotes the פסוקים *Pesukim* again right before
the משנת אליהו *Mishnat Eliyahu*. דבמלכים כתיב ויקח יהוידע הכהן ארון אחד
ויקב חור בדלתו ויתן אותו אצל המזבח מימין *Dabmelakhim ketiv vayyikkah yehoyada
hakkoben aron ehad vayyiqqov hor bedalto vayyitten oto etsel hammizbeah miyyamin*. Right.
ובדברי הימים ב' פרק כ"ד כתיב ויאמר המלך ויעשו ארון אחד ויתנהו
בשער בית ה' החוצה *Uvdivre hayyamim bet pereq kaf dalet ketiv vayyomer
hammelekh vayya'asu aron ehad vayyittenehu beshaar bet hashem hahutsa*. So one says
that they put it אצל המזבח *Etsel haMizbeah*. So here's partly an
answer to your question. מימין אצל המזבח *Miyyamin etsel haMizbeah* is not
so accessible to most people. The other says they put it in
the שער בית ה' החוצה *Shaar bet Hashem hahutsa*, which is outside
of the door, which is much more accessible. So עשה רב יונתן
אומר שתי נדבות עשה *Asa Rav Yonatan omer shte nedavot asa*, there
were two different types of boxes. Okay, doesn't exactly explain why and
what they were used for. תני דבי רבי ישמעאל *Tanni devei Rabbi
Yishmael* נדבה nedavah. אחת *Nedavah ahat* דכתיב ויאמר המלך ויעשו ארון אחד
ויתנהו בהיכל בית ה' ויקב חור בדלתו *Dekhtiv vayyomer hammelekh vayya'asu aron
ehad vayyittenehu behekhal bet Hashem vayyiqqov hor bedalto*. Okay, and that was
the one that says they put it on the right of
the מזבח mizbe'ach. *Mizbeah*. וכתיב ויאמר המלך ויעשו ארון אחד ויתנהו בשער
בית ה' החוצה *Ukhthiv vayyomer hammelekh vayya'asu aron ehad vayyittenehu beshaar bet
Hashem hahutsa*. So it sounds like a different location. So אמר amar:
רב הונא מפני הטמאים *Amar Rav Huna mipne hatemma'im*. So they put
it there so so take a look again the קרבן korban העדה
*Korban HaEdah* explains top line מפני הטמאים *Mipne hatemma'im* לעולם נדבה nedavah?
אחת היתה *Leolam nedavah ahat hayetah* אלא שיהוידע נתנו בפנים *Ella sheyehoyada
natano bifnim*. So יהוידע *Yehoyada* originally was put by the מזבח mizbe'ach,
*Mizbeah*. And then the next פסוק *Pasuk* says ויאמר המלך ויתנהו בשער
בית ה' החוצה *Vayyomer hammelekh vayyittenehu beshaar bet Hashem hahutsa*. אבל המלך
אמר amar: שיתנהו בחוץ כדי שיוכלו גם הטמאים דהיינו טמאי מת ושרץ
ולפניהם *Aval hammelekh amar sheyyittenehu bahuts kede sheyyukhlu gam hatemma'im dehaynu tamme
met vesherets vlifnehem*. Okay, so he actually reads it's not just טמאים
*Tamma'im* but it's actually the king overrode what the כהן גדול Kohen
Gadol *Kohen Gadol* did. כהן גדול Kohen Gadol *Kohen Gadol* wanted it
in the עזרה *Azarah*, which limited the access, and the king said
no, put it on the outside of the gate so even those
that are טמאי *Tamei* they could still be on הר הבית Har
HaBayit, *Har HaBayit* but they can't be in the עזרה *Azarah*, everybody
would have access to it. אמר רב הונא מפני הטמאים *Amar Rav
Huna mipne hatemma'im* אמר רב הונא בשם רב יוסף אך לא יעשה
בית ה' ספות כסף מזמרות *Amar Rav Huna beshem Rav Yosef akh
lo ye'aseh bet Hashem sippot kesef mizmarot*. Not exactly clear what he
wants to do by just ending by quoting that פסוק *Pasuk*. Okay,
so so
fine, so that is the end of that פרק *Perek*. The קרבן
korban
העדה *Korban HaEdah* says the reason he quoted the פסוק *Pasuk* if
we look at the קרבן korban העדה *Korban HaEdah* again he has
the גירסא על שם *Girsa al shem* he says כלומר על כרחך
לומר דשתי נדבות היו *Kelomar al korhakha lomar deshte nedavot hayu*. Actually
they were two נדבות *Nedavot*, it wasn't one that was moved. דמלכים
כתיב אך לא יעשה בית ה' ספות מזמרות מן הכסף המובא בית
ה' *Demlakhim ketiv akh lo ye'aseh bet Hashem sippot mizmarot min hakkeseph
hammuva bet Hashem*. One says they would not use the money for
buying כלי שרת *Klei sharet*. ובדברי הימים כתיב וככלותם את שאר הכסף
עשו כלי שרת *Uvdivre hayyamim ketiv ukhkhallotam et sh'ar hakkeseph asu klei
sharet*. Okay, so if you look at it, it says two different
locations where the boxes were put, and actually also says that one
of it says it was not used for the כלי שרת *Klei
sharet* and the other says it was used for the כלי שרת
*Klei sharet*. So clearly we are talking about two different donations, two
different boxes, okay, some used for one purpose, some used for another
purpose. הדרן עלך פרק י"ג שופרות shofarot, *Hadran alakh pereq yud gimmel
shofarot*. So that is the different places in which moneys were put,
one of it being of course the שקל shekel *Shekel* or two,
old shekel new shekel, but then a lot of other issues about
where moneys were put and that leads us into this פרק *Perek*
which gets us into an interesting question of you don't know where
the money came from. So let's take a
look. משנה Mishnah *Mishnah*. מעות שנמצאו בין השקלים לנדבה Maot shenimtzu bein
hashekalim lanedavah. *Maot shennimtseu ben hashqalim linnedavah*. So if you found some
coins that were between the שופרות shofarot, *Shofarot* for שקלים shekalim *Sheqalim*
and the שופרות *Shofarot* for נדבה nedavah *Nedavah*. Now of course as
we're going to see in the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* it's a little
hard, I gotta inaugurate our new board, okay, but anyway, right, it
said that you had your שופרות *Shofarot*, okay. שהחיינו *Sheheheyanu*, thank you.
תקלין חדתין
*Taqlin hadtin*, okay and then you'd have your תקלין עתיקין *Taqlin atiqin*
or whatever, and then the next one was anybody remember what the
next one was? Was it the גוזלי סינים *Gozle sinim*? No, קינים
kinnim, *Kinnim*, קינים kinnim *Kinnim*, right? and then it was גוזלי עולה
gozley olah. *Gozle olah*, גוזלי עולה gozley olah
*Gozle olah*, and then what you have you had you had I
think
you had the עצים etzim *Etsim*, לבונה levonah. *Levonah*. One, two, three,
four, five, six, and
one more, no, two more, one more. Okay, so it says you
found a coin and that coin was between the שופר shofar of
שקל shekel, and נדבה. nedavah Problem. Those are the ones that are
furthest from one another. You could say you found a coin between
old and new שקל, shekel between שקל shekel and קינים, kinnim between
קינים kinim, and גוזלי עולה. gozlei olah, What do you mean between
שקל shekel and נדבה? nedavah, The גמרא Gemara will discuss how that
happens. Oh, you figured it out! So the גמרא Gemara is going
to say that they were aligned in a circle, right? And if
they were aligned in a circle like that, so the last six
of נדבה nedavah. would be here and שקל shekel would be here
and you found a coin over here, and those are the various
boxes. Okay, but that's what the גמרא's Gemara going to say. Very
good. You figured it out.
Okay, look at that board, fantastic.
Amazing.
מעות שנמצאו בין השקלים לנדבה. l'nedavah. So you found money between the
שקל shekel box and the נדבה nedavah. box. קרוב לשקלים יפלו לשקלים.
Karov lashekalim yiplu lashekalim. If it's closer to the שקל shekel box,
you put it in the שקל shekel, box. לנדבה יפלו לנדבה. Lanedavah
yiplu lanedavah. To the נדבה, nedavah, you put it in the נדבה.
nedavah. This is a principle amongst the various principles we have of
how to determine ספקות. sfekot. We all know of רוב rov and
חזקה, chazakah, but there's an interesting principle that you don't know about
so much called קרוב, karov, which is a very logical one which
is if there's a question where something came from, we can assume
that it came from the closest place. If there's a question about
ownership and we have my pigeon, we have a pigeon between our
two pigeon coops and we're debating whose it is, okay, or this
is a ritual issue, how is it sanctified and which הקדש hekdesh
purpose do you apply it to? So you go by קרוב karov
and the גמרא Gemara they learn it out, בבלי Bavli they learn
it out from the whole idea of והיה העיר הקרובה vehayah hair
hakerovah by the חלל, chalal, right, that the city that is closest
to this dead body, whatever, is assumed to be the one that
is responsible for it.
That's my favorite סוגיא sugya in ש"ס Shas because רבי ירמיה Rabbi
Yirmiyah says what if the pigeon has one foot in and one
side in...
right! And they said על דא הוציאו לרבי ירמיה מבי המדרש. al
da hotziu l'Rabbi Yirmiyah mibei hamidrash. רבי ירמיה Rabbi Yirmiyah was a
נודניק. nudnik. Okay, anyway.
So okay. So לנדבה יפלו לנדבה. Lanedavah yiplu lanedavah. מחצה למחצה, Mechtza
l'mechtza, if it's exactly halfway, see that's רבי ירמיה's Rabbi Yirmiyah case,
exactly halfway between something like that, יפלו לנדבה. yiplu lanedavah.
So if you have a doubt you put it in the נדבה.
nedavah. So the גמרא Gemara is going to ask by all of
this, the משנה Mishnah is going to tell you what you do
if you don't know, but the question is why? Why is that
the better choice of the two? Okay, this by the way it
also raises, right, it also raises you know Charlie's question which he
asked before, which I still need to give you an answer about,
which is why you can't just solve some of these issues by
פדיון? pidyon? Say, okay, you know make a תנאי. tnai. If that
coin is נדבה, nedavah then the value is transferred to this coin.
If it's not, then המקדיש hamakdish this coin is נדבה. nedavah. And
if the coin is שקל, shekel. then the value transfers to this
coin, and if not המקדיש hamakdish this coin is שקל. shekel Then
you know this one is שקל shekel and this one is נדבה.
nedavah. So that's a very good question why you can't solve it
all by doing a conditional פדיון pidyon and have and know at
the end result you'll have one of each. Okay, but that's not
what the משנה Mishnah. says. Okay. בין עצים ללבונה, Bein etzim lilevonah,
if it's between the box for the wood and the one for
the frankincense, קרוב לעצים יפלו לעצים, Karov laetzim yiplu laetzim, ללבונה יפלו
ללבונה. lilevonah yiplu lilevonah. If it's closer to one you put it
in that
one. מחצה למחצה Mechtza l'mechtza 50-50, יפלו ללבונה. yiplu lilevonah. You put
it in the לבונה. levona Well again, not clear why, but the
גמרא Gemara will discuss. בין קינים לגוזלי עולה, Bein kinnim legozley olah,
between the קינים kinim which we said according to רבי מאיר Rabbi
Meir argued on רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda that was for חטאת chatat
עולה olah pairs as opposed to גוזלי עולה gozlei olah. which were
birds that were just עולות. olot. קרוב לקינים יפלו לקינים, Karov lakinnim
yiplu lakinnim, קרוב לגוזלי עולה יפלו לגוזלי עולה. karov legozley olah yiplu
legozley olah. מחצה למחצה Mechtza l'mechtza if it's half and half, I
mean right in the middle, יפלו לגוזלי עולה. yiplu legozley olah. You
go to עולה olah which is again interesting.
Why? The last case is the easiest, it actually moves away from
these boxes. בין חולין למעשר שני. Bein chullin lemaaser sheni. In your
home you found money between the box, the chest in which you
keep your normal funds and the one in which you keep your
מעשר שני maaser sheni money. Okay, we're no longer in the בית
המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. מעשר שני Maaser sheni money is money that has
to be brought to ירושלים, Yerushalayim, it was used to redeem fruit
and you'd buy food and you'd eat it in ירושלים. Yerushalayim. So
קרוב לחולין יפלו לחולין. Karov lachullin yiplu lachullin. If it's closer to
the חולין chullin box, you put it in that or whatever wallet
you put it in that. למעשר שני Lemaaser sheni if it's if
it's closer to the מעשר שני maaser sheni like you know money
pouch, יפלו למעשר שני. yiplu lemaaser sheni. מחצה למחצה Mechtza l'mechtza if
it's smack in the middle, יפלו למעשר שני. yiplu lemaaser sheni. Now
that's an obvious one, that's a no-brainer. זה ספק, Zeh safek, you're
מחמיר. machmir. זה הכלל הולכין אחר הקרוב להקל. Zeh haklal hochin achar
hakarov lehakel. If there is one that is closer we will go
by it even if it means being more lenient assuming this is
חולין chullin funds. מחצה למחצה Mechtza l'mechtza if there's not one that's
closer להחמיר lehachmir you always you play it safe and you take
מחמיר. machmir. So the again, the point is is that here you
understand there's an easy easy sense of how to just play it
safe. In the earlier cases it's not so easy and we'll see
in the גמרא Gemara that it'll try to explain some of those
earlier decisions. Yes, Michael?
Isn't the other considerations come into play that let's say I find
like מעשר שני maaser sheni fund and you know most of my
dealings now...
yes, and that'll be the next משנה. Mishnah Okay, so good question.
Okay, רוחא דצריכא. Ruacha d'tzericha. So the גמרא Gemara says
דלא בין שקלים לנדבה. delo bein shekalim lanedavah. It basically says again
the, you know, it should've said or, you know, it wasn't needed
to say but it doesn't need to sort of like say the
opposite. Shouldn't it have said that you found money between שקלים shekalim.
and קינים, kinim right? Because the קינים kinim, were right next, right,
to the שקלים. shekalim That's where it should've said. Maybe if, you
know, in the end it doesn't make such a difference, although there
it does make a difference too, but why didn't it how did
it talk about the שקלים shekalim and the נדבה nedavah. which were
all the way at the end of the line? So רבי אבהו
בשם רבי פנחס Rabbi Abbahu b'shem Rabbi Pinchas כמין ברוכליא היו עושין.
k'min brukhliya hayu osin. It was made like a circle. There's a
question exactly what ברוכליא brukhliya means. It's some type of a vessel
that's circular, but clearly the answer is it was made like a
circle. Now, of course, it doesn't exactly answer the question because it
explains how you have the scenario of between שקלים shekalim? and and
נדבה. nedavah? It does not explain why you didn't describe the other
scenario as well, right? Both scenarios are possible, right? So it allows
for that scenario, but it doesn't explain why it didn't give you
the other scenario and and the גמרא Gemara is not going to
answer that. Now we're going to talk about the rest of the
משנה Mishnah about why what meaning even if it's a circle, right,
if it's a circle, you can have the שקל shekel between שקל
shekel? and נדבה. nedavah That's a possible scenario, so it's acceptable that
the משנה mishna. discussed it, but it still didn't discuss this scenario,
right? It discussed this scenario, קינים וגוזלי עולה. kinim v'gozlei olah. It
discussed what did it discuss after קינים וגוזלי עולה?
kinim v'gozlei
olah?
That was it, right? What no, לבונה ועצים. levonah v'etzim. So it
discussed לבונה ועצים, levonah v'etzim, but there's a lot of things it
didn't discuss. It didn't discuss שקל וקינים, shekel v'kinim, it didn't discuss
גוזלי עולה ועצים, gozlei olah v'etzim, and it didn't discuss לבונה וזהב,
levonah v'zahav, and it didn't discuss זהב ונדבה, zahav v'nedavah, right? It
discussed like, you know, two or three out of about seven or
eight possible scenarios. All right, so anyway, but at least it allows
for that case. מחצה למחצה יפלו לנדבה. Mechtza l'mechtza yiplu l'nedavah.
Now, half and half it goes to the נדבה. nedavah Now, why
is it? So the so again, we'll read the parentheses that makes
the question clearer. וצריכה דאמר מחצה למחצה יפלו לשקלים. V'tzrikha d'amar mechtza
l'mechtza yiplu l'shekalim. Why? I don't get it. Why don't we say
that if it's a doubt, it goes to the שקל? shekel Why
does it go to the נדבה? nedavah Why is the נדבה nedavah
a better sort of way of playing it safe between נדבה nedavah.
and שקלים? shekalim, So איבעית אימא, ee ba'it eima, some want to
say, שמא יפלו לשירי הלשכה shema yiplu l'shirei halishka because if it
goes to the שקלים, shekalim, what could wind up happening to the
money? If you put it in the שקלים, shekalim where's the שקלים
shekalim, funds going to be used? So you'll say, "Oh, it's used
for קרבן ציבור." korban tzibbur. That's, you know, if it goes to
if it was meant as נדבה nedavah. funds, like the way of
thinking about what would be the worst-case scenario, right? So if it
was meant as נדבה nedavah funds and you used it as שקלים,
shekalim you should say, "Oh, that's a pretty good choice because that'll
be used as a קרבן ציבור." korban tzibbur. That certainly maybe just
as good or better than being used as a נדבה. nedavah Maybe
that's included in the idea of נדבה. nedavah, But no, because what
if the money gets leftover? And if the money gets leftover, right,
remember only some of the money is used for and what do
you do with שירי הלשכה? shirei halishka? You build use it to
build up the walls of ירושלים. Yerushalayim. So if that was the
if that maybe is implicit in the שקל shekel, donations that the
leftover funds can be used for those more very general purposes. But
if I gave money for a נדבה nedavah for a קרבן עולה,
korban olah, there's no way that money can now be used to
build up the walls of ירושלים. Yerushalayim. So we can't allow for
the fact that this might be נדבה nedavah? money and we're going
to put it in the תרומה trumah money and then it'll be
leftover תרומה trumah money and then it'll go for these very non-הקדש
hekdesh uses, which might be, again, stipulated for the שקל, shekel but
it would not be for the שקל shekel but it would not
be acceptable for this. Okay, so that's one reason, שמא יפלו לשירי
הלשכה. shema yiplu l'shirei halishka. איבעית אימא, ee ba'it eima, and someone
want to say, מחצה למחצה כמי שמת. mechtza l'mechtza k'mi shemet. Fifty-fifty
is like you're dead. I'm sure you could use that in some
metaphoric way, being undecided is anyway. But no, what it means is
what happens if and the גמרא Gemara is going to say, somebody
okay, if somebody gave a שקל shekel and then they died, okay,
people die throughout the year and their שקלים were already donated. That's
the idea that it becomes money of the ציבור. tzibbur. But let's
say somebody didn't give it yet. ראובן Reuven set aside his שקל
shekel. to give and he's מחצה השקל. mechtza hashekel. He said, "This
is going to be" ראובן Reuven said, "This is going to be
my שקל." shekel And then ראובן Reuven dropped dead before the money
even made it to the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. What would you
do with that? Can you give that as a שקל shekel donation,
you know, into the hands of the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash although
it's already been sanctified after the person is dead or not? And
we are going to see that according to one opinion, what you
do with that is like what you do with a lot of
funds when they can't be used, which is what? Like what do
you do with a חטאת chatas when the owner died, right? Or
the well, חטאת chatas is the animal that's actually sanctified, but if
there's leftover money or an אשם asham and the owner dies, it
goes לנדבה. l'nedava. It goes exactly to this fund of being used
for these עולות. olos. So what he's arguing is that a שקל
shekel as well, if the owner died and can't be used, would
get transferred to this fund. So this money that you don't know,
is it a שקל shekel, or a נדבה, nedavah is essentially like
a if it were שקל, shekel it's like a שקל shekel that
the owner died. It's a שקל shekel that can't be used as
a שקל shekel. because you don't know that it's a
שקל. shekel, No, no, no, there's two scenarios. One is he separated
and he died. Gets transferred into עולה olah funds, the נדבה nedavah
funds. The other is you don't know: is it a שקל, shekel
is it a נדבה? nedavah. So he says it's analogous to separating
and died. It's like a שקל shekel. that can't be used. It
can't be used because we don't know if it's a שקל. shekel
So the basic ruling is he says a שקל shekel that can't
be used gets converted to נדבה nedavah funds like we see by
חטאת, chatas, like we see by אשם, asham, and that's why it
goes לנדבה. l'nedava. Okay, let me just read
it: איבעיא להו מחצה ונדבה כמי שמת. isbaiya lehu mechtza unedavah kemi
shemeis. אמר רבי יוסי אנה דאתא תמן—while amar Rabi Yossi ana de'asa
saman I was there in בבל, Bavel, we've had this phrase
before: שמעת קליה דרבי יהודה שאל לשמואל. shamas kalaya deRabi Yehuda sha'al
liShmuel. We had the same idea: I heard the voice of רב
יהודה Rav Yehuda asking שמואל. Shmuel. Previously when we had it before,
you tried to say that maybe the אמורא Amora was the blood,
but this is because of—but that's not true here, it was רבי
יוסי. Rabi Yossi. So anyway, it was good—it was a good thought.
It seems to be a ירושלמי Yerushalmi idiom. Anyway, I heard the
voice of—it's but before also, if my memory serves, it was also
the same source: רב יהודה Rav Yehuda asking שמואל. Shmuel. So it's
interesting, this phrase: I heard the voice of רב יהודה Rav Yehuda
asking שמואל. Shmuel הפריש שקלו
ומת—somebody hifrish shiklo umes set aside their שקל shekel and
died. אמר ליה—so amar lei what do you do? He says: יפלו
לנדבה—it yiplu linedavah goes to the נדבה nedavah funds. So that's his
answer. His answer is, you know why? Because if it were a
שקל shekel that maybe—that—that can't for some reason be used, the הלכה
halacha is it gets converted to נדבה. nedavah That's just—נדבה nedavah, seems
to be this catchall of what you do with certain funds that
can't be used in their original purpose, and that's why here it
would go לנדבה. So that's his answer. The other answer again is
that you can't have the נדבה nedavah go to שקל shekel because
it might be used for a de-sanctified purpose, whereas if it's the
reverse—it was given as a שקל shekel? and now it's used for
נדבה—that's nedavah still being used for a קרבן korban purpose, so that's
still seen as a better, you know, a safer bet for that
than the other way. What's not explained is, it's nice that it's
a safer bet, but at the end of the day, was it
a legitimate use of the שקל? shekel Can money sanctified for a
שקל shekel, be used for נדבה, nedavah you know, or not? But
anyway, at least there you're more in the פרשה parsha than the
possibility that it would actually be put to חולין chulin use, which
could happen if you went in the opposite direction. And the other
answer is a very simple—that's just the הלכה: halacha: it gets converted
into that type of a fund if you can't use it.
Yeah, you're essentially along those lines, like,
you know,
someone
מפריש mafrish
his
שקל, shekel he dies, he has one son, so that son can't
use it for his own שקל—I shekel. mean, he inherits the guy
anyway. No, I mean, the son has to—everybody—person has to give their
own שקל. shekel You mean he inherits it, but it's already הקדש,
hekdesh, so it's not, you know—so he doesn't inherit. Yeah, I mean,
it's like if somebody's מקדיש makdish an עולה, olah, his son will
bring it, but he's bringing it not as his own עולה, olah,
he's bringing it for the father. He can't use it for his
own עולה. olah. It's already been given its identity. Okay, now, עשירית
האיפה שלו—now asirit ha'eiphah shelo for some reason this gets—seemed to be
just tagged on, that this was part, presumably, what רב יהודה Rav
Yehuda asked שמואל about what do you do with certain things that
can't be used for their original purposes. So let's say the כהן
גדול Kohen Gadol separates his עשירית האיפה, asirit ha'eiphah, which is the
מנחה mincha the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol would bring—his personal מנחה mincha
every day—and then he died. What do you do with that, or
what do you do with the money that he sanctified for it?
So רבי יוחנן Rabi Yochanan אמר: יוליכם לים המלח. yolichem leYam HaMelach.
That doesn't get to be converted into נדבה nedavah funds; that gets—you
have to just throw it out into the ים המלח, Yam HaMelach,
you have to dispose of it, you can't convert it into anything.
Is it because he's a—it's another כהן Kohen that was appointed?
Yeah, whatever, and this came up before—I don't want to get into
this now—this is just really like a—just a tangent of the previous
one. רבי אליעזר Rabi Eliezer אמר: יפלו לנדבה. yiplu linedavah. And here
again we have the idea: no, a נדבה nedavah, can be a
catchall. So without getting into what the issues are by the עשירית
האיפה, asirit ha'eiphah, again you see this idea that the נדבה nedavah
can serve as a type of a catchall category for certain things
that cannot be used for their original purpose. And that's why it's
easier, if there's a doubt, to put the money into the נדבה
nedavah box. Okay, now the גמרא Gemara moves on to the second
case.
So someone said this is an anonymous נדבה, nedavah we don't know
from—no, no, no.
The כהן גדול Kohen Gadol
separates out his עשירית האיפה asirit ha'eiphah and then he drops dead,
or separates out money for his עשירית האיפה asirit ha'eiphah that he
has to give every day—every day the כהן גדול has to bring
an עשירית האיפה—and asirit ha'eiphah then he drops dead. What do you
do with that money? It's his personal קרבן korban and it's sanctified
and he's no longer around to bring it. So can that convert
into a נדבה nedavah or not? Okay?
Right, so when it converts into a נדבה—yeah, nedavah. the כהן גדול
is no longer alive. Right, so somebody's going to offer that.
Yeah, but no, no, no. נדבה nedavah, means these six נדבה nedavah.
boxes. It means generically free—it's not personal נדבה. nedavah, Ah, it's money
that's given over to the communal fund of bringing these קרבנות. korbanot.
It's not transferred into—no, no, no.
The whole point of that phrase נדבה, nedavah like, is the same
as the phrase קיץ המזבח, kaits hamizbeach, which means it is not
your personal קרבן korban anymore. It means that it is now the
communal funds that are used to bring these קרבנות. korbanot. Okay, so
we did with the שקל shekel and the נדבה. nedavah Okay, now
we're going—again, it doesn't have all the scenarios—but now we're going to
between the קינים kinim and the גוזלי עולה, gozlei olah? and it
says you go to the גוזלי עולה. gozlay olah Now the problem
is two questions. Number one: if it was a חטאת chatas fund,
how can you use חטאת chatas fund for גוזלי עולה? olah, By
the way, it's a little similar to the fact that חטאת chatas
money leftover can be used for נדבה, ndava right? But that's by
non-birds. But anyway, here you have something similar. If it was money
that was partly
חטאת... chatas... used for an עולה, olah? so there's something comparable there,
but the other question that's going to be asked besides if it
was קינים, kinim. how do you use it to this is the
poor woman that put her money in here and is expecting her
קרבן korban to be brought, right now that money is going to
be put into this box, there's not going to be a קרבן
korban that is going to be brought for that person, right? So
one somebody is not getting their קרבן korban brought for them and
is not becoming טהור. tahor. So how do you deal with that?
That's a really big problem.
Right, so let's take a look at what the גמרא Gemara says.
So, קשיא, Kasha, ויש חטאת קריבה עולה. V'yesh chatas krevah olah. So
first it asks the first question: if it was חטאת chatas money,
how can you סתם stam use it as an עולה? olah, Again,
there's a principle like מותר חטאת mosar chatas comes an עולה, olah.
but this is straight חטאת chatas money and it's also by birds
which tends to have different rules. חזקיה בשם ריש לקיש, Chizkiyah b'shem
Reish Lakish, so now here's your catch-all answer: תנאי בית דין הוא
על המותרות שיקרבו עולות. Tnai Beis Din hu al hamosaros she'yikrevu olos.
Ah, בית דין Beis Din stipulates that any leftover funds for, you
know, for חטאת chatas should become as an עולה. olah. You know,
that's true about cows and sheep or whatever. Leftover funds for חטאת
chatas becomes goes into the נדבה ndava. box, and similarly here, like
we sort of said by the מחצית השקל, Machshis HaShekel, ah we're
just going to stipulate that any leftover funds, any doubtful funds that
are going for חטאת chatas in the end get converted into עולות.
olos. So we just make the rules. Okay, and we sort of
stipulate everybody who sanctifies at the end of the day plays by
our rules, sort of like כל המקדש אדעתא דרבנן מקדיש. kol hamakdish
ada'ata derabbanan makdish. Okay, so כל המקדיש אדעתא דרבנן מקדיש. kol hamakdish
ada'ata derabbanan maktish. You said that last time. Okay, good line, I
stole it from you. Okay, so you're playing by our rules. Okay,
so now the גמרא Gemara has a question. Fine, that allows it
to be converted to an עולה. olah. But what about the poor
woman who needs her חטאת chatas brought? So let's take a look.
האישה הזאת במה מתכפרת. Ha-ishah hazos bamei miskapara. Where does this woman
get her how her קרבן korban, brought for her? It's one thing
you made a נדבה ndava and it's a freewill and it didn't
get brought because the money got misplaced. But it's another thing if
you without your קרבן korban you're not finished your purification process. So
אמר רב יצחק, Amar Rav Yitzchak, תנאי בית דין הוא. Tnai Beis
Din hu. Now what is תנאי בית דין הוא? Tnai Beis Din
hu? Her קרבן korban wasn't brought. So here's the תנאי בית דין
Tnai Beis Din and
this is better
because this is more דיני ממונות dinei mamonus rules. המספק את הקינים,
Hamesapek es hakinim, the supplier of the birds, okay, הוא מספק את
הפסולות ואת האבודות. hu mesapek es hapsulos v'es ha'avudos. He has to
supply birds even for animals that get lost and that are invalid,
which means what? You come over to me and again exactly how
it works, you know, let's say בית דין Beis Din takes their
funds and they've got their שופר filled with the money for the
bird עולות, olos, okay also by the חטאת chatas we'll get to,
and they have a hundred dollars and the birds are going a
dollar each and they give it to Michael there who's the supplier
and he has to give us a hundred birds to bring these
נדבות for all of our קיני גוזלות kinay gozalos that we have
here, גוזלי עולה ola that we have here. Then we start bringing
the birds and we realize oh look this one is missing a
limb and then one minute I thought we had a hundred we
only have ninety-eight. So we go back to Michael and we say
you know what Michael we know you gave us a hundred but
three of them were פסול pasul and four got lost. And Michael
has to give us seven now back. He has to make it
up. If you're going to be the supplier for the בית המקדש,
Beis HaMikdash, as we've seen before what you exchange for very high
volume and regular business is unfavorable, you know, sort of trading conditions.
So what? Walmart? Walmart. So Michael has to make up any lost
or פסול pasul birds even if he's supplied us the initial amount.
Now once that's true what we can include in that condition is
if we have this box and we have a coin here and
we didn't know which box it goes to, we get to say
to Michael, Michael you know we only have ninety-eight dollars in our
in our קינים kinim box but it might have been ninety-nine. We
don't know about one coin and Michael has to give us ninety-nine
birds. Okay so since we're going to get the extra bird anyway
we will bring so the money gets put into here, okay, and
that money then goes to the supplier to buy that number of
עולות. olos. But here we don't have that coin but he has
to supply us this number plus one because that coin might have
been in that box. Okay so the woman is protected, the קרבן
korban is brought, it's only Michael who's out his money. But if
I supply both then I have to give another one in, do
I? Yes you do. Yes you do, that's the condition. Even though
I... Yep, that's the condition. Okay, we get to make the rules.
Is there any rules where is this woman first mentioned? No, it's
assumed before what mentioned קני זבים, kanei zavim, you know, קינים. kinim
The standard קינים kinim is a woman who gives childbirth, okay, it's
a regular occurrence or, and that's like the standard assumption, one bird
for חטאת, chatas, one for an עולה. ola. All right, so okay.
And there's no issue of like order? Like you know which one
you make first and the timing and... No, it's all beyond that's
all מסכת קינים. Masechet Kinim. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like
this, okay: לא צריכא דלא בין קטורת לעצים וללבונה לזהב לכפרה. Lo
tzericha d'lo bein ktoret l'etzim u'l'levona l'zahav l'kapara. Gemara says what about
all the cases you didn't mention about money being found between the
קטורת ktoret and the עצים eitzim, or between the לבונה levona and
the זהב לכפרה? zahav l'kapara? All the other types of scenarios also
wasn't mentioned. So the גמרא Gemara says ותניא בסיפא, v'tanya b'seifa, it
doesn't matter to include in the last statement. זה הכלל הולכין אחר
הקרוב מחצה למחצה להחמיר. Zeh haklal holchin achar hakarov mechtza l'mechtza l'hachmir.
Just do everything להחמיר. l'hachmir. But the question is, what's להחמיר? l'hachmir?
I mean, it's all החמרות. hachmirot. How do we know what להחמיר
l'hachmir is? And none of that is explained. What also isn't explained
is the case about if it's between the לבונה levona, and the
עצים, eitzim right, what does it say it goes to? It goes
to the לבונה, levona right? Is that right? מחצה למחצה, mechtza l'mechtza,
so why is that? We still don't know, right? He starts to
explain, this goes to נדבה ndava because שקל shekel gets converted to
נדבה. ndava, You know, this goes to the עולה ola because also
here, questionable חטאת chatat money gets converted to עולה. ola, But we
didn't discuss עצים eitzim and לבונה levona. why it goes to לבונה.
levona, And if it was some of these, which is the מחמיר
machmir one? We don't know. So the רמב"ם Rambam says interestingly that
actually the reason, not like the גמרא Gemara, says, the גרא Gra
tries to explain how the רמב"ם Rambam reads the גמרא, Gemara but
the reason שקל shekel, goes to נדבה ndava, and the reason קינים
kinim, go to עולה ola, is because that's להחמיר. l'hachmir. Why is
that להחמיר? l'hachmir? Because when you bring an עולה, ola. that's considered
being a more
מחמיר machmir use,
it all gets used by the מזבח. So if you have it
between שקל, shekel, although most קרבנות ציבור korbanot tzibur are עולה, ola,
some are חטאת. chatat. So it's more מחמיר machmir to put it
to נדבה where it's all עולה. ola. If you have it between
קינים and go to עולה, ola this is a חטאת, chatat, half
a חטאת, chatat, all of this is עולה. ola That's more מחמיר
machmir and עולה's ola fully burnt up. So presumably עצים eitzim and
לבונה, levona remember I told you the הלכה halakha is, if you
just say I'm bringing a קרבן, korban, we assume it means לבונה
levona because לבונה's levona fully burnt up. Now why that's more, עצים
eitzim are also fully burnt up, but maybe לבונה's levona a bit
more of a קרבן korban than עצים which are also like the
fuel. Okay? What it would be between this, לבונה levona and the
gold, or the gold and the נדבה, that I don't know. But
לבונה is actually a קרבן and you'd say it should go to,
presumably then you would go to, the קרבן would be better than
just something used in the בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. And then זהב
zahav and נדבה, again, עולה olah would get a preference. So that's
the basic idea that עולה olah, and קטורת ktoret always get the
preference. But it's very funny that the גמרא Gemara does not explain
to explain
what the, we don't have to say it, it's just להחמיר. l'hachmir.
Does רמב"ם Rambam go through these cases? Does he enumerate them individually?
I'd have to check, I don't remember. I could check. Okay. So
let's take a look at the next משנה. mishna מעות שנמצאו לפני
סוחרי בהמה. Maot shenimtzo'u lifnei sochrei beheima. So this is a משנה
mishna that's known even to learners of the בבלי Bavli because it's
quoted a lot in the בבלי. Bavli. Okay, money that is found
before people that sell animals in ירושלים, Yerushalayim, לעולם מעשר. le'olam ma'aser.
You assume no matter what the time of the year is that
it's מעשר ma'aser funds because presumably you'd bring up a lot of
money for your מעשר שני ma'aser sheni money, you could bring
up your מעשר שני ma'aser sheni at any time during the year,
there wasn't only one time in the year you could bring it
up, and you'd have so much money, I mean imagine that you
have thousands of acres, and you could have like ten thousand dollars
a tenth of your produce that year, could be ten thousand dollars
worth. You bring it up to ירושלים, Yerushalayim, how long are you
going to spend in ירושלים Yerushalayim to eat ten thousand dollars worth
of food? So you have all this leftover money, so you distribute
it, you distribute it to friends, relatives, maybe you give it to
the עניים. ani'im. There's a lot of מעשר שני ma'aser sheni money
running through ירושלים Yerushalayim throughout the year. And the assumption is, and
of course מעשר שני ma'aser sheni you could use any food for
it, you could do anything, but the assumption is that people want
to bring the מעשר שני ma'aser sheni money because the פסוק says
ואכלת לפני ה' אלקיך, v'achalta lifnei Hashem Elokecha, and a classic type
of אכילה לפני ה' achila lifnei Hashem is שלמים. shelamim. That's לפני
ה' lifnei Hashem and there's the אכילה לפני ה'. achila lifnei Hashem.
That's why the גמרא Gemara says that the שמחת יום טוב simchat
yom tov is אכילת שלמים, achilat shelamim, because it has the idea
of eating in the presence of God. So the גמרא Gemara assumes
or the משנה mishnah. assumes that מעשר שני ma'aser sheni money would
all be used, most often be used to buy animals to bring
as שלמים. shelamim. So therefore, again it's a fascinating assumption, there's so
much מעשר שני ma'aser sheni money and it's regularly used to buy
animals, that any money found in the שוק shuk of the butchers
should be assumed to be מעשר שני ma'aser sheni money. That's where
all the מעשר שני ma'aser sheni money wound up. Okay.
Does it depend if it's פסח Pesach or?
It says it doesn't matter the time of the, oh, you mean
before פסח Pesach it might be specifically something else? Maybe. But generally
regardless of the time of the year it's מעשר. ma'aser. Okay, ובהר
הבית חולין. uv'har habayit chullin.
But if the money is found on the הר הבית, Har HaBayit.
that's חולין, chullin, because you're not buying your animals on the הר
הבית. Har HaBayit? Now of course the question is what are you
doing with money on the הר הבית? Har HaBayit You're not supposed
to go up on the הר הבית Har HaBayit with your money
pouch. We'll discuss that. ובירושלים, uv'Yerushalayim, now in the rest of ירושלים,
Yerushalayim, בשאר כל ימות השנה חולין, bish'ar kol yemot hashana chullin,
during the normal time of the year it's חולין. chullin. You know,
it's just money on the ground. ובשעת הרגל, uv'sh'at haregel,
but during the time of the רגל, regel, הכל מעשר. hakol ma'aser.
Then you have to assume that it's מעשר ma'aser fund because then
again everybody is bringing, you know, everybody's coming up רגל regel and
everybody has their מעשר ma'aser money to use. Now why if that's
true, if during the time of the רגל regel you have throughout
ירושלים, Yerushalayim, not just in front of the butchers, throughout ירושלים Yerushalayim
it's, you know, everybody has מעשר ma'aser money on them, why don't
you assume that's true about הר הבית Har HaBayit as well during
the רגל regel that it's all מעשר ma'aser money? Right, you understand
the scenario? Throughout the year by the butchers it's always going to
be מעשר ma'aser money. In the rest of ירושלים Yerushalayim it'll be
סתם. stam. But in general everybody has מעשר *maaser* money and that's
what it is. So say the same on הר הבית Har HaBayit,
*Har Habayis*. So the story's like this. In ירושלים Yerushalayim, *Yerushalayim*, they
had the same problem we have in New York, which is they
had street cleaning every single day. So they didn't have to worry
about alternate side of the street parking, but what it did was
it said that you could assume that any funds, anything that was
found was recent. So therefore if in ירושלים Yerushalayim. *Yerushalayim*, if you
find money, you could assume it fell from somebody's pocket recently, because
otherwise it would have been swept up the day before. So therefore
if it's recent and it's the time of the רגל regel, *Regel*,
you can assume it's מעשר *maaser* money. Whereas if it's on הר
הבית Har HaBayit *Har Habayis*, it might be the time of the
רגל regel, *Regel*, but this money might have been here for weeks
or for months. They didn't sweep הר הבית Har HaBayit? *Har Habayis*
regularly. Now that's a little bizarre. They swept ירושלים Yerushalayim *Yerushalayim* and
not הר הבית Har HaBayit *Har Habayis*? But הר הבית Har HaBayit
*Har Habayis* had two things going for it. Number one is people
could not walk up to the הר הבית Har HaBayit? *Har Habayis*
with dust on their feet. So it wouldn't need sweeping. And number
two is it was on a slope and it was windier and
so on. So because הר הבית Har HaBayit. *Har Habayis* was not
swept regularly, you went by the regular year regardless of the time
because the money could just as well or more likely be old
than new. But in ירושלים *Yerushalayim* you assumed that it was newly
dropped and it would depend on what time of year in terms
of what its identity was. Yes, Charlie.
מעשר שני ma'aser sheni, *Maaser Sheni* is given the first, second, fourth,
and fifth year of the שמיטה *Shmita* cycle? Correct. So the other
years?
Would it still be the same? Presumably yes because as I said
you had tons of this money and you had and you your
opportunity to use it would be when you took your visits to
ירושלים *Yerushalayim*. And you presumably you know it's like when you come
back from Israel and you have a hundred shekel left over and
you say what do I do I stick it in my drawer
with my passport? So the next time I go I'll have the
hundred shekel. So that's what you did. You had all this מעשר
שני *Maaser Sheni* money. Every time you went to ירושלים *Yerushalayim* you
took some of it with you so you could pay for your
food that time.
שעת הרגל *Sh'at ha-Regel* wouldn't you assume שעת הרגל *Sh'at ha-Regel* it's
a חגיגה *Chagigah*?
Well that's sort of like Michael's question. It could be but more
most of the money was using up all their מעשר שני *Maaser
Sheni* money. I mean it's fascinating to realize everybody has to bring
the קרבן עולה olah *Korban Olah*, everybody has to bring the חגיגה
*Chagigah*, but okay that's one קרבן *Korban*. But there's apparently tons of
money coming into ירושלים *Yerushalayim*. That's the assumption. I know it's a
fascinating assumption.
It's really not so easy.
Okay so let's take a look. Now that's in terms of money.
Now בשר הנמצא בעזרה *Basar HaNimtza BaAzarah*. Now let's say you find
meat. It's meat in the Temple courtyard. In the Temple courtyard the
only meat there was for the meat that the כהנים kohanim *Kohanim*
ate which was the חטאת chatat, *Chatas* and the אשם *Asham*. So
אברים *Eivarim*, but there could also be עולות *Olos* which would be
burnt on the מזבח *Mizbeach*. So if it's a limb, if it's
quartered into limbs, that's עולות *Olos*, then you burn it on the
מזבח *Mizbeach* because that's what it would that's how it would look
like an עולה *Olah*. You would dismember it. חתיכות *Chatichos*, if it's
like a steak like a slice of meat, then חטאות *Chataos* you
assume it's a חטאת chatat, *Chatas*.
So why can't it be the שלמים shelamim *Shelamim* that like was
cut up?
Because that would wouldn't be in the עזרה *Azarah*. The בעלים *Bealim*
would take it
out of the עזרה *Azarah*
because it's a קדשים קלים *Kodshim Kalim*. Yeah but I mean presumably
it's immediately taken out whereas the only meat that stays around is
from the חטאת chattas, *Chatas* and the עולה *Olah*. ובירושלים *U'v'Yerushalayim*, and
now but if it's in ירושלים *Yerushalayim*, זבחי שלמים *Zivchei Shelamim*, you
assume it's שלמים *Shelamim* meat because that's what you would do. Now
interestingly you more assume that it's שלמים *Shelamim* meat in ירושלים *Yerushalayim*
than you assume it's... if everybody is buying בהמות *Behemos* with their
מעשר שני *Maaser Sheni* money, okay but remember if you're buying בהמות
*Behemos* with your מעשר שני *Maaser Sheni* money it's in order to
bring it as a שלמים *Shelamim*. So in a way it it
reinforces what we said before. The money in front of the butchers
is all מעשר שני *Maaser Sheni* money because everybody's using that money
to buy meat to bring שלמים *Shelamim*. And therefore the meat that
you find is also assumed to be שלמים *Shelamim* and not to
be סתם stam חולין chulin. *stam chullin* meat. Okay now what do
you do with it? זה וזה תעבור צורתו ויצא לבית השרפה *Zeh
v'zeh taavor tzuraso v'yeitzei l'veis hasreifa*. Either way though you don't know
that it was left today, it might have been left yesterday. It
might be נותר *nosar*. So regardless of whether you think it's a
שלמים *Shelamim* an עולה *Olah* or חטאת *Chatas* you have to wait
a day to make sure it's definitely נותר *nosar* because maybe it's
not נותר *nosar* today. And so you wait a day, you wait
till it's definitely נותר *nosar* and then you burn it. Okay so
of course the question is as the רמב"ם *Rambam* says when he
brings this down if you're going to burn it anyway why do
I care if it's an עולה *Olah*, חטאת *Chatas* or שלמים *Shelamim*?
Right you're going to burn it. So he says well you care
because if בדיעבד *b'dieved* you ate it and you didn't burn it
we want to know what's in it for you.
Or if you did a sin or not. Okay anyway. לבית השרפה
*L'veis HaSreifa*, that's a place like there's there's a place in the
בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash *Beis HaMikdash* that you would actually burn פסולי
קרבנות korbanot *psulei korbonos*. I mean...
Is it in the עזרה *Azarah*?
In the... ליד המזבח *lyad hamizbeach*?
I'd
have to remember exactly what its location is.
Is it another... is it another small... it's like an altar?
No it's not an altar. What is it? A place, so like
it's a place, a pit, a room, whatever, yeah that they would
burn it. I'll have to get you its exact location but it's
basically on Temple grounds. Okay. נמצא בגבולין Nimtza bigvulin. *Nimtza Bagvulin*, if
it's found right outside of the what do you call it, if
it's found right outside of ירושלים *Yerushalayim*, אברים *Eivarim*, so if it's
limbs, נבילות *neveilos*, you assume it's a נבילה neveilah, *neveila*. Why? Because
you don't bother chopping up a נבילה neveilah, *neveila* into steaks. Okay
now why would you dismember it? Because you gotta get rid of
it. Like you throw it to the dogs, you sell it maybe
to the non-kosher butcher, but you're not going to bother to chop
it up into steaks. So if it's limbs you assume it's a
נבילה neveilah *neveila*. And חתיכות *Chatichos*, if it's like chops of meat,
מותרות mutaros, *muttaros*, then it's kosher. Again, this is assuming that you
find it like in a Jewish community, you know, you have to
assume in general it starts, you know, it's starting within that context,
so the only concern is maybe it was a פסול pasul? שחיטה,
maybe it was a טריפה, treifa, but if there's no reason to
assume that, you can actually assume that it's kosher meat. ובשעת הרגל
שהבשר מרובה אף איברים מותרות. Uvesha'as haregel shehabasar merubeh af evarim mutarot.
At the time of the רגל, this is not about קרבנות korbanot,
of the רגל, this is about because everybody's having a meat meal
for יום טוב, Yom Tov, okay, then even if it's in large,
like a leg of lamb, you can assume that, you know, there's
a lot of wholesaling and retailing going on, and you can assume
that even if it's not chopped up into steaks, even a big
limb is also ultimately kosher and it's just because of the amount
of meat that's not all chopped up.
ובשעת הרגל Uvesha'as haregel is
not about קרבנות, it's about יום טוב Yom Tov outside of ירושלים,
people would eat meat. It's definitely outside of ירושלים. Okay, so now
let's go to the case about the money that on הר הבית
Har HaBayit. you don't have, it's חולין. chulin? So the גמרא Gemara
says like this: לא צריכא דלא בהר הבית קודש. Lo tzricha d'lo
behar habayit kodesh. So the גמרא Gemara says, wait a minute, if
it's on הר הבית, you know, what did we just learn is
going on in הר הבית with money? What's most of the money
on הר הבית? קודש! Kodesh! There's all this money which is הקדש,
hekdesh, שקל, shekel, קינים, right, all this, there's tons of money going
into the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash area on הר הבית that is
קודש. kodesh. So how is it that if I find money on
הר הבית I can assume it's חולין? chulin Okay, pretty good question,
forget מעשר שני, what about all this stuff? So the גמרא Gemara
says: רבי בא רבי חייא בשם רבי יוחנן חזקה שאין הכהן מוציא
מן הלשכה מעות עד שהוא מחללן על בהמה. Rabbi Ba, Rabbi Chiya
beshem Rabbi Yochanan chazaka she'ein hakohein motzi min halishka ma'ot ad shehumechalal
al beheima. Similar to like some claims we made before, yes, as
soon as this money was taken out of the boxes, it was
immediately, you know, transferred to the object they were going to use
it for. So
they
did not have a lot of funds, like the הקדש hekdesh funds
would be in the שופרות, right, but they did not have a
lot of funds that were הקדש hekdesh that were once they were
out of the שופרות, because as soon as they were taken out,
they were transferred. Of course, the question is what about before they
were put in? They were still הקדש. hekdesh. So maybe it assumes
that you didn't sanctify it, which would make sense. Until the minute
you get there, you made a donation, I, a person takes a
נדר, neder, I'm going to give so much money, right, and then
they come to the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash and they give, and
here's my שקל, shekel right, they don't, it's stupid to sanctify things
ahead of time because then you can just lead to problems, just
wait to the last minute. But it's still an interesting question because
is it really, could you so assume that nobody is bringing הקדש
hekdesh funds up to the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash during all of
this? Okay, so that's the question. The other question I should mention
that gets asked is what are people doing with any money up
on הר הבית? Right? You know?
So, no, because the גמרא Gemara says you don't
bring your money belt up on הר הבית. So תוספות Tosafot raises
this in a few places and תוספות's Tosafot answer is you can't
have your money belt, but you can have like money. You just
can't have it in a very sort of like business type of,
you know, the type of thing that more is like the type
of things you would wear that really suggest commerce and business and
so on. But to have actual some money in your pocket, loose
change, whatever, that would be okay. Another explanation could be that you're
not bringing up the money, that the money is this money that
got transferred the קדושה, kedusha, and now it's the חולין money and
that fell down, like maybe the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash, used this
money and it brought the קרבן, again we gave it to Michael,
our pigeon supplier, and now Michael has a hundred שקל that's been
desanctified. So he didn't bring the money up with him, but he's
got now this money on him to use. Okay, but still, I
mean the money got there somehow so there is money that is
being brought up on the הר הבית.
Okay, yes, just the way you reason, you read the Hebrew, it's
really לא צריכא דלא בהר הבית אלא קודש, lo tzricha d'lo behar
habayit ela kodesh, right? Is that what it means?
Yeah, is
it like a difference between
אלא קודש? ela kodesh? Well, or lo, it's sort of like the
גמרא Gemara says לא צריכא, lo tzricha, which is like shouldn't you
be saying the following?
Right, but then what do you have that second negative for?
לא צריכא דלא בהר הבית אלא קודש, Lo tzricha d'lo behar habayit
ela kodesh, I guess,
right, hard to read, yeah. Okay, now בשר שנמצא. basar she'nimtza.
Now we skip to the meat. Okay, again, the money interest issue
was very interesting about the assumptions about people that are selling the
בהמה beheima and all these issues about ירושלים that it was swept
regularly and the new money, skips over all of that and we
go to the meat. So בשר שנמצא. basar she'nimtza. רבי אליעזר בשם
רבי הושעיה: Rabbi Eliezer beshem Rabbi Hoshaya: הסיח דעת טעון עיבור צורה.
hisiya da'at te'un ibbur tzurah. Now why is it that when you
find the meat and you don't know which קרבן it comes from,
or you do it mapse, you assume that it's an עולה or
a שלמים or חטאת, whatever you assume, why is it that you
have to wait a day? Why can't you just, and make it
become פסול? pasul. Why can't you just use it? If it's an
עולה, burn it on the מזבח, if it's a חטאת, let the
כהנים eat it. So I told you, this was the reason that
the גמרא Gemara is going to say, which is the easy reason,
because you don't know if it's from today or yesterday, it might
already be פסול. pasul. But what the גמרא Gemara is now saying
is it's not because you don't know whether it's new or old,
let it be today, but because you stopped paying attention to it,
בשר קודש basar kodesh that you had הסח הדעת, hesach hadaat, okay,
the בבלי Bavli says הסח... hesach... That lack of attention itself invalidates
it. So even if it's today's meat, today's חטאת, you can't eat
it. Today's עולה you can't bring it, cause since it was left
unattended, that made it פסול. pasul Okay, הסח הדעת תני עיבור צורה.
hessech hadaas tani ibur tzura. אמר רבי הושעיה מתניתין אמרה כן. Amar
Rabbi Hoshaia masnitin amrah ken. That's implicit in our משנה. mishnah? עבר
צורתו ויצא לבית השרפה. Ibar tzuraso v'yeitzei l'veis hasreifah. It says that
you've got to burn it and wait till it becomes פסול pasul
and you burn it and you can't go ahead and eat it
or offer it up today. אמר רבי יוסי, Amar Rabbi Yosi, ויאות,
Veya'os, is that really proper, is that really the correct read of
the משנה? mishnah. No, there's another reason why you have to make
it wait and make it פסול pasul. and burn it and you
can't assume it's כשר. kasher. Not because of הסח הדעת. hessech hadaas.
לאוכלו אי את יכול, L'ochlo ein ata yachol, because you can't eat
it, שמא נתקלקלה צורתו. shema nitkalkela tzuraso. Again the phrase קלקול צורה
kilkul tzura or עבר צורה ibar tzura means that it's a day
old and it's לינה. linah. It's starting to change. Right, it's like
exactly, it's not fresh. It's not fresh, it's not fresh. So the
point is maybe it's a day old. It has nothing to do
with הסח הדעת. hessech hadaas. The reason you can't eat it or
offer it is because it might be already פסול. pasul ובגין כן
צריך מימר עבר צורתו ויצא לבית השרפה. U'vgin ken tzarich meimar ibar
tzuraso v'yeitzei l'veis hasreifah. So you don't burn it now, because it
might still be כשר, kasher, but you wait till it becomes פסול
and then you burn it. Okay. All right. נמצא בגבולין. Now, meat
outside of the בית המקדש, we can assume it is, if it's
in limbs, then it might be נבילה, neveilah, but if it's chopped
into slices, then it is considered to be כשר. kasher. So רב
כריספיא בשם רבי יוחנן בשם רבי חנינא איברים נבילות לוקין עליהם משום
נבילה. Rav Krispia b'shem Rabbi Yochanan b'shem Rabbi Chanina eivarim neveilos lokin
aleihem mishum neveilah. It's not just we חושש choshesh that it's a
נבילה, neveilah, we're certain that it's a נבילה neveilah, if it's in
limbs. That's like a חזקה chazakah that only an animal like that
would only be in this state if it was a נבילה, neveilah.
otherwise it would be chopped up into slices, and if somebody ate
it, they would get lashes. It's a real חזקה. chazakah. So the
גמרא Gemara says מתניתין אמרה כן. Masnitin amrah ken. You know what,
it's implicit in our משנה. mishnah, איברי נבילה וחתיכות איברי נבילה חתיכות
מותרות. Eivarei neveilah v'chatichos eivarei neveilah chatichos mutaros. So that's the משנה,
right? If it's the limbs, it's a נבילה, neveilah. if it's chopped
up into slices, it's permissible. The גמרא says חתיכות מותרות. chatichos mutaros.
When it says that the chops of meat are permissible, לא ממש,
lo mamash, it means fully permissible. It doesn't mean like theoretically permissible,
it means you can eat it. It's really permissible. So דכוותיה, Dechvaseih,
by parallel, איברי נבילה, eivarei neveilah, when we say the איברים eivarim
are נבילה, neveilah. we don't just mean it's a חשש נבילה. chashash
neveilah. לוקין עליה משום נבילה. Lokin aleha mishum neveilah. We mean it's
real נבילה. neveila So yes, this is a complete assumption, it's not
just a חומרא, chumra, and therefore it's with real consequences. Okay. Now
we have some exceptions to this. רב כריספיא בשם רבי יוחנן בשם
רבי חנינא,
Rav Krispia b'shem Rabbi Yochanan b'shem
Rabbi Chanina, אם היו מחרוזות, im hayu machruzot, if they were strings
of meat, okay, מותרות, meaning even if they were limbs, if they
were all strung together on some type of a cord, right, then
clearly it's coming from the butcher house. It's not the way you
would treat a נבילה. neveila? Then it would be permissible presumably. Okay,
now we get into famous בבלי Bavli discussion about the nine shops.
תשע חנויות. Tesha chanuyos. You have nine butcher shops מוכרות בשר נבילה,
mochros basar neveilah, they all sell טריפה. treif. ואחת מוכרת בשר שחוטה,
V'achas mocheres basar shechuta, one sells כשר kasher meat. נתחלף לו. Nischalef
lo. So if you don't know where you bought it from, חושש,
choshesh, you then you have to be concerned, you got it from
the טריפה treif one, especially in this case nine are טריפה. treif.
ונמצא, V'nimtza, but if you just find it on the ground and
you don't know where it came from, הלך אחר הרוב, holech achar
harov, you go by the majority. Now in both ways they're both
אסור, asur, but the difference is, if it's on the ground, you
go by רוב. rov. This is the הלכה halacha that if it's
קבוע, kavuah, you're trying to figure out which store, and the stores
have fixed locations, it's כמחצה על מחצה. k'mechetzah al mechetzah. So ironically,
even though nine stores are טריפה, treif, if you don't remember which
store you bought it from, it's only a ספק נבילה. safek neveilah.
It's considered a 50/50 doubt. But if it's on the ground, then
you go by רוב rov and then it's treated as a ודאי
נבילה. vadai neveilah. Okay, so in one case you would you would
be אסור asur but you wouldn't get lashes, and the other case
you'd get lashes. Now in the flip, this is a more obvious
difference. תשע חנויות מוכרות בשר שחוטה, Tesha chanuyos mochros basar shechuta, nine
sell כשר kasher meat, ואחת מוכרת בשר נבילה, v'achas mocheres basar neveilah,
and one sells נבילה. neveila נתחלף לו, Nischalef lo, if you don't
remember which store you bought it, that's the principle of קבוע, kavuah,
fixed stores, you don't remember which one you went to, חושש, choshesh,
you have to be concerned even though it's only one out of
nine, you can't eat the meat. ונמצא, V'nimtza, if it's on the
ground and it's more of an abstract question, where did it come
from, and not a question of which store did I go to,
so in that question when it's כל דפריש, kol d'parish, הלך אחר
הרוב holech achar harov and you could actually eat it. Okay. אמר
רבי יוחנן הנמצא ביד נכרי כנמצא בפלטיה. Amar Rabbi Yochanan hanimtza b'yad
nochri k'nimtza b'palatya. Let's say you find it in the hand of
a נכרי. nochri. He says that's like finding a non-Jew has meat,
he says, "I asked my non-Jewish friend or servant to go buy
some meat," he doesn't remember where he bought it from, okay, do
we say since he doesn't remember where he bought it from, it's
like I don't remember where I bought it from and it's the
principle of קבוע כמחצה על מחצה, kavuah k'mechetzah al mechetzah, because you
go by the shops and they're fixed? Or do you say, no,
he does not have a halachic question, I'm the one that has
a halachic question, so when it's in his hand, it's like I
found a piece of meat on the ground. He forgets where he
went. He tells you, I don't remember where I went. Oh, I
was supposed to pay attention, Rabbi, I was supposed to? Okay. So,
נמצא ביד נכרי כנמצא בפלטייא, nimtza be-yad nochri ke-nimtza be-paltya, it's like
being found in the town square. And it's therefore you go by
this principle of כל דפריש מרובא פריש. kol de-parish me-ruba parish. It's
not like you don't remember which store and you have to say
fifty-fifty. רבי אלעזר בירבי חגיי הוה מסמיך לרבי מנא. Rabbi Elazar be-rebi
Chaggai hava masmich le-Rabbi Mana. Rabbi Elazar be-rebi Chaggai was supporting Rabbi
Mana as they were walking on the way. He was getting elderly.
חמא לחד ארמיי, chama le-chad armai, he saw a certain non-Jew, מקטי
מן סוסיה, maktei min susya, he cut off meat straight from his
horse. Okay, ומפיק לבר, u-mafik le-bar, he took it outside. So now
he's got a question. When a non-Jew has meat, how do we
say, well, you know, maybe it came from this store or that
store, you go by רוב? rov? Who says that they only get
it from stores? Maybe they're cutting up their dead horses in their
barns. Okay, so אמר ליה, amar lei, הדא דאמר רבי יוחנן, hada
de-amar Rabbi Yochanan, נמצא ביד נכרי כנמצא בפלטייא. nimtza be-yad nochri ke-nimtza
be-paltya. How do you go? What do we say if you find
it in the street? You go by the majority of stores. פרוש
הולך אחר הרוב. parash holech achar ha-rov. But he says, who cares
about stores? Maybe they're getting it from dead animals in their barns.
So אמר ליה, amar lei, כן אמר רבי יוסי, kein amar Rabbi
Yosi, והן שראן יוצאין ממקולין של ישראל. ve-hen she-ra'an yotzin mi-makolin shel
Yisrael. Okay, you know what? You're right. If you just saw him
סתם with meat and you have no idea where it came from,
maybe you couldn't go by the majority of stores. We're talking that
he came from the square of butchers. He came from the butchers'
market. You know he got it from a butcher; you just don't
know which butcher. And that's when we say you go by the
majority of butchers. One last story: חד בר נש בציפורי, chad bar
nash be-Tzippori, a certain person in ציפורי, Tzippori, אזל בעי מזבן קופד
מן טבחא. azal ba'i mizban kupad min tavcha. He wanted to buy
meat from a שוחט. shochet. ולא יהב ליה, ve-lo yahav lei, and
the שוחט shochet refused to give it to him. They were fighting.
He said, I'm not going to sell you meat. So אמר ליה
לחד רומאי, amar lei le-chad romai, so the guy who wanted to
buy says to his friend, the Roman, go get, buy me meat
in that store. ואייתי ליה, ve-ayiti lei, and he brought him meat.
So he thought, ah, I tricked him. I got somebody else to
buy the meat for me. So אמר ליה, amar lei, so the
purchaser went to the butcher and said, לא נפשת על כרחך, lo
nafisat al karchach, hey, I tricked you! I managed to buy meat
from you against your will. אמר ליה, amar lei, so he said
back to him, דלאו בשרא דנבילה יהבית ליה, de-lav basar de-neveila yahavit
lei, I gave him נבילה neveila meat! So now, so maybe I
figured out what you were doing. So now the question is: now
can we, do we have to be concerned that maybe all the
meat this guy sells is נבילה? Has he now undermined his trustworthiness
because he says he sells כשר kosher meat and he sold this
non-Jew נבילה meat? So that's the question it ends with. רבי ירמיה
בשם רבי חנינא, Rabbi Yirmiya be-shem Rabbi Chanina, מעשה בא לפני רבי.
ma'aseh ba lifnei Rebbe. Rebbe, the question was brought to Rebbe, what
do we have to do now? Do we have to concern this
guy sells נבילה meat? דאמר, de-amar, לא כולם מיני אסר מקולין דציפורי.
lo kulam minei me-asar makolin de-Tzippori. We cannot, not based on his
report are we going to forbid the butchers of ציפורי. Tzippori. Just
because he said that this is what he did, maybe it'll hurt
his own store, but we're not going to start raising questions about
everybody else's business practice. What about the rest of the stuff that
he sells in his store? Not clear about his store, but everybody
else's store we're certainly not going to raise any questions about. Okay,
to be continued.